Readium CSS Fundamental Concepts

[Implementers’ doc] [Authors’ info]

This document serves as an introduction, it explains the fundamental concepts used in designing Readium CSS.

1. We’re the User Agent

In the context of EPUB, we must assume the role of the User Agent.

Indeed, EPUB is not supported natively so we must build on top of web browsers’ rendering engine.

With such a role comes great responsibility: we must try to behave like browsers are behaving – i.e. be liberal in what we accept from authors –, and find a sensible balance between authors’ stylesheets and users’ overrides.

Authors and users have expectations though, and we had to take those into account. For instance, they are used to having EPUB contents laid out in a paged view, with reading modes (paper, sepia, night) and a minimal set of common settings.

By serving as a User Agent, we must make sure:

authors’ EPUB contents are rendered as expected (e.g. their styles are scoped, we don’t override them unless strictly necessary, etc.);
we do serve as a user’s agent by providing a Graphical User Interface to writing a user stylesheet (i.e. user settings) and applying those styles as expected.

2. Aim at Interoperability

Interoperability is the logical result of the User Agent role we’re claiming.

We’ve done our utmost to follow EPUB and CSS recommendations to the letter, but it vastly depends on practical implementations. As a consequence, Readium CSS ships with its own recommendations, so that you don’t need to check every related specification yourself.

Besides, we’ve checked other major EPUB implementations to provide authors with the best interoperability possible. Indeed, they may design their stylesheet against those implementations so we gave priority to building a reliable environment.

We wanted to bring EPUB closer to the web though, and decided to leverage HTML5 Suggested Rendering and improve the current situation whenever possible.

3. Leverage Modern CSS

CSS has a lot to offer nowadays, and it can help solve complex issues in simpler ways.

Readium CSS has been be designed following 4 core principles:

Modularity: Readium CSS is not a monolithic stylesheet but a set of modules;
Separation of Reading System’s Concerns: those modules are task-oriented e.g. paginate, apply default styles, intercept styles for reading modes or user settings, apply a reading mode or user setting, apply a theme, etc.;
Daisy-chainability: those modules can be loaded and daisy-chained (cascade) depending on conditions;
Customization: modules can be customized either before or during runtime (CSS variables), which implies themes can be generated within minutes.

4. Openness and Transparency

This last principle is important since the relationship between authors and Reading Systems’ developers has not been really great so far.

Therefore, feedback has been collected, samples have been used all along development, and decisions impacting authors have been openly discussed. All of this has been publicly documented during research and development.

More importantly, we must clearly state what is UA styles and user styles, and why !important is used. This process has a significant impact when it comes to transparency since it affects the cascade itself (see user settings recommendations). Should an author file an issue scoped to your implementation, please take the time to explain why you decided to differ and use !important, especially as such a decision can likely be backed by users’ feedback in many cases.

Quickstart

[Implementers’ doc]

Readium CSS is a set of reference stylesheets for EPUB Reading Systems. It provides styles for reflowable text:

a CSS normalize for EPUB contents;
paged and scrolled views;
default styles;
reading modes (night, sepia, etc.);
themes;
user settings;
media overlays and user highlights.

Note: Readium CSS stylesheets were not designed and should not be used for fixed-layout EPUB, nor other file formats like FB2, PRC, Mobi, TEI, etc.

Important info

TL;DR: use the stylesheets in the css/dist folder if you don’t need to customize Readium CSS. All the flags and variables can then be taken at face value in the docs.

The src files, which are modules, can’t be used AS-IS. They indeed have to be processed by PostCSS to create dist stylesheets.
By default, those modules are daisy-chained and compiled into 3 dist stylesheets:

ReadiumCSS-before.css;
ReadiumCSS-default.css (for unstyled ebooks);
ReadiumCSS-after.css.

We’re currently managing RTL and CJK (including horizontal and vertical writing) scripts using specific dist stylesheets:

Right to Left stylesheets are distributed in an rtl folder;
CJK horizontal stylesheets are distributed in an cjk-horizontal folder;
CJK vertical stylesheets are distributed in an cjk-vertical folder.

The build process is currently subpar as it has been designed for our default and must be changed entirely if you want to process and use modules directly – which would make sense with HTTP2 for instance.

How To

Inject ReadiumCSS stylesheets into the <head> of (X)HTML documents.

ReadiumCSS-before.css
Authors’ stylesheet(s) or ReadiumCSS-default.css for unstyled publications
ReadiumCSS-after.css

Check the Stylesheets order doc for further details.

For RTL, you would then have to load the stylesheets in the rtl folder. Same for CJK. Check the “Internationalization” doc for guidance.

By default, we inject all stylesheets on load and rely on custom properties (a.k.a. CSS variables) set on html to apply user settings.

Customize

ReadiumCSS ships with a ReadiumCSS-config.css file you can use to customize it a little bit. It allows implementers to:

define in which conditions the auto pagination model is used;
choose selectors for the user settings’ flags.

In order to provide this customization, we use custom media and custom selectors, which will hopefully become standards implemented at some point, but require PostCSS at the moment. Consequently, you’ll have to rebuild all dist stylesheets if you’re changing this file.

Auto pagination model

The auto pagination model switches from 1 to 2 columns, and vice versa, when the conditions defined in ReadiumCSS-config.css are met. Further details about this model can be found in “Injection and pagination” doc.

On desktop, --responsive-columns is the min-width at which the model must be used. Default is 60em, a relative unit since it is responsive by default and will switch depending on the window’s dimensions and the font size.

Should you want it never or always applied, you can either define a min-width large or small enough, or remove the media queries entirely in ReadiumCSS-pagination.css and ReadiumCSS-colNumber_pref.css.

On mobile, --min-device-columns and --max-device-columns is the range of (minimum and maximum) device widths in which the model must be used. We are forcing the orientation in landscape.

We recommend not trying to apply it in portrait orientation because 2 columns will provide users with quite a terrible reading experience in this configuration.

Those custom medias may be extended at some point, depending on implementers’ feedbacks and issues.

Flags for user settings

By default, we are using flags in the form of CSS variables to manage reading modes and user settings. But you might want to customize those flags in order to use custom attributes (data-*) or good old CSS classes.

A complete list of flags can be found in the User preferences doc.

As an example, if you want to use a CSS class for night mode, it could look like:

@custom-selector :--night-mode .night-mode;

And if you want to use custom attributes for advanced settings, it could look like:

@custom-selector :--advanced-settings [data-settings="advanced"];

Both would then have to be appended to html at runtime.

Once again, you must rebuild dist stylesheets.

Add and remove modules

We have to add and remove modules depending on the language/script of the publication so this need is covered out of the box.

In the css/src folder, you’ll find all the needed stylesheets you will process to css/dist. Those stylesheets contain a list of imports e.g. for ReadiumCSS-before.css:

@import "../ReadiumCSS-config.css"; 
@import "modules/ReadiumCSS-base.css"; 
@import "modules/ReadiumCSS-day_mode.css"; 
@import "modules/ReadiumCSS-fonts.css"; 
@import "modules/ReadiumCSS-html5patch.css"; 
@import "modules/ReadiumCSS-safeguards.css";

As a consequence, modules you want to use have to be listed in those -before and -after files. Then rebuild them using PostCSS.

Additional user settings MUST be added to the user-settings-submodules folder, and make the required flag clear, if applicable.

Please remember to take the cascade into account, as issues might arise just because the order has been changed or modules moved from -before to -after – in which case we won’t be able to reproduce and debug an issue if we don’t know this important detail. See Stylesheets order doc for further details.

Reading System variables

If you want to change the name of --RS__ prefixed variables, you will have to change it in every module.

Build dist stylesheets

First, please make sure you have node.js installed. If you don’t, go download it on the official page.

Then navigate to the readium-css folder in your terminal and type:

npm install

This will install all dependencies needed to build dist stylesheets.

Once you have customized src files, in the terminal type:

npm run-script build

This will rebuild all dist stylesheets in their specific folder.

Options

Other scripts are available:

build:ltr for default stylesheets (Left to Right);
build:rtl for Right to Left stylesheets;
build:cjk for CJK scripts;
build:vertical for CJK and the Mongolian scripts in vertical writing.

Additional info

Further details about the build and test processes can be found in the npm doc.

User settings variables

If you want to change the name of --USER__ prefixed variables, you will have to change it in every module.

Manage User Settings

Currently, user settings are managed by setting CSS variables at the :root level (html element).

Flags

At the top of each user settings submodule, you will find the required flag for the preference.

This flag is needed for the setting to work.

User variables

All settings can be set using --USER__ prefixed variables. Set those properties for html and the cascade will automatically do its job.

To set a variable:

var root = document.documentElement || document.getElementById("iframe-wrapper").contentWindow.document.documentElement; 
root.style.setProperty("--USER__var", "value");

To remove a variable:

var root = document.documentElement || document.getElementById("iframe-wrapper").contentWindow.document.documentElement; 
root.style.removeProperty("--USER__var");

Please note you must implement a fallback strategy if you want to support Internet Explorer 11 and early versions of Microsoft Edge.

Examples

Changing hyphenation and justification

root.style.setProperty("--USER__advancedSettings", "readium-advanced-on"); 
root.style.setProperty("--USER__textAlign", "justify"); 
root.style.setProperty("--USER__bodyHyphens", "auto");

Of course this example is simplistic. You could for instance create an helper to set multiple properties at once.

Changing the type scale

You might want to change the type scale in order to adjust the font-size of all elements to the size of the screen and the global font-size set by the user. It can indeed help solve overflow issues for long words in headings, ridiculously large sizes, etc.

root.style.setProperty("--USER__advancedSettings", "readium-advanced-on"); 
root.style.setProperty("--USER__typeScale", "1.067");

Create Themes

In this model, themes are a set of user settings you can store and retrieve. Add the properties to html and you get a theme.

Check the User Preferences doc for a list of available user variables.

How the multicolumn layout works

[Implementers’ doc] [Authors’ doc]

Global References:

W3C Spec
W3C Mailing List — css-multicol

Introduction

By using columns, content can flow from one column to another, and the number of columns can vary depending on the size of the viewport. The specification was originally designed to replace table-based multicolumn layout.

You can declare a multicolumn layout with one line of CSS:

body { column-width: 15em; }

Or

body { column-count: 2; }

Or

body { columns: 2 15em; }

The multi-column model

Multi-column layout introduces a new type of container between the content box and the content: the column box. This is a significant departure from the traditional box model.

The content of a multicol element is flowed into column boxes, which are arranged into rows, like table cells (inline direction). Consequently:

column width is the length of the column box in the inline direction;
column height is the height of the column box in the block direction;
all column boxes in a row have the same column width and column height;
adjacent column boxes are separated by a column gap, which may contain a column rule;
all column gaps (and column rules) in the same row are equal;
column rules only appear between columns that both have content.

Critical shortcomings can be pointed out in the column box model:

it is not possible to set properties/values on column boxes, which is why you can’t set the background of one specific column;
the column box has no concept of padding, margin or borders;
column boxes don’t establish containing blocks for elements with position: fixed || absolute;
multicol elements with column heights larger than the viewport may pose accessibility issues.

However, floats inside multi-column layouts are positioned with regard to the column box where they appear.

Finally, since a multi-column element establishes a new block formatting context, a top margin set on the first child element will not collapse with the margins of the multicol element.

The number and width of columns

Basically, two properties determine the width of columns:

column-count;
column-width.

A third one, columns, is a shorthand which sets both.

Column width

This property describes the width of columns in multicol elements.

Its values can be:

auto, which means the column width will be determined by other properties (column-count if set);
<length>, which describes the optimal column width.

The actual column width may be wider (to fill the available space), or narrower. But the column width can only be narrower if the available space is smaller that the specified column width.

Notes

To ensure that column-width can be used with vertical text, column width means the length of the line boxes inside the columns.
To set an exact column width, all length values (width, column-width, and column-gap) must be specified.

Column count

This property describes the number of columns of a multicol element.

Its values can be:

auto, which means the number of columns will be determined by other properties (column-width if set);
<integer>, which describes the optimal number of columns into which the content of the element will be flowed.

It is important to note that if both column-width and column-count have non-auto values, the integer value describes the maximum number of columns.

Columns

This is the shorthand property for setting column-width and column-count. Omitted values are set to their initial values (auto).

Pseudo-algorithm

The pseudo-algorithm below determines the used values for column-count (N) and column-width (W). There is one other variable in the pseudo-algorithm: the used width of the multi-column element (U).

The used width of the multi-column element (U) can depend on the element’s contents, in which case it also depends on the computed values of the column-count and column-width properties. The specification does not define how U is calculated.

(01)  if ((column-width = auto) and (column-count = auto)) then
(02)      exit; /* not a multicol element */
(03)  if column-width = auto then
(04)      N := column-count
(05)  else if column-count = auto then
(06)      N := max(1,
(07)        floor((U + column-gap)/(column-width + column-gap)))
(08)  else
(09)      N := min(column-count, max(1,
(10)        floor((U + column-gap)/(column-width + column-gap))))
(11)  W := max(0, ((U + column-gap)/N - column-gap))

What is important to understand there is that the column-width can either be a floor or a ceiling, depending on the value of column-count.

Let’s take some examples.

/* Condition starting at line 3 applies */ 
body { column-width: auto; column-count: 2; }

The column width is not set, it entirely depends on column-count and column-gap (which suggested default is 1em).

Columns theoretically have a floor (which is suggested to be 1px or less) and a ceiling (line 11)

/* Condition starting at line 5 applies */ 
body { column-width: 300px; column-count: auto; }

In this example, the number of columns is computed depending on the column width and gap.

In other words, the column width is a ceiling: it can’t be larger than 300px but can shrink if the available width is less.

/* Condition starting at line 8 applies */ 
body { column-width: 300px; column-count: 2; }

In this example, the column width is a floor: if 2 columns (2 × column width and the gap) can fit, column-count will be honored, else column-width grows to the width available. If there is additional width available when 2 columns fit, column-width will grow as well.

It’s worth noting that the used value for column-count is calculated without regard for explicit column breaks or constrained column heights, while the actual value takes these into consideration.

Stacking contexts

Column boxes do not establish new stacking contexts.

Column gaps and rules

What is important is that column gaps take up space while column rules don’t.

column gaps will push apart content in adjacent columns (within the same multicol element);
if there is a column rule between columns, it will appear in the middle of the gap.

As regards column rules:

they are painted just above the background of the multicol element so that child elements with z-index values to be on top of column rules;
they are only drawn between two columns that both have content.

Fragmentation (column break)

This has been moved to the CSS Fragmentation module.

When a page or column break splits a box, the box’s margins, borders, and paddings have no visual effect where the split occurs. It is important to remark outline and box-shadow are not discussed at all in the spec.

In the previous spec, it was stated that “the margin immediately after a forced page or column break will be preserved” but that isn’t necessarily the case in practice, CSS authors often having to resolve to padding-top to force a margin after a page break.

From experience, avoiding a break-inside elements flowing in 2 or 3 columns can also be problematic (the element vertical alignment is completely off).

Column span

You can only span all columns or none. It is not possible to declare an <integer>.

An element establishes a new block formatting context if its column-span is set to all. In other words, column-span kind of resets the flow to the first column.

We may not necessarily worry about this (in authors’ CSS) because the User Agent can treat it as column-span: none if it can’t find room to make the element spanning. Constraining the height of columns should be enough to prevent a column span, especially with overflow.

Filling columns

By default, columns will be balanced (minimal variation in column length), they won’t be filled sequentially.

This default can be overridden with

body { column-fill: auto; }

It’s worth noting User Agents should try to honor widows and orphans in any case.

Overflow

What is important to remark is that:

content that extends into column gaps is not clipped to the column box;
a multicol element can have more columns that it has room for, additional column boxes are created in the inline direction (page or column break, constrained height, etc.);
columns that appear outside the multicol element are called overflow columns.

Reflow

CSS multicol relies on a complex (fragmentation) logic, and this logic varies for each browser.

In Blink and Webkit for instance, a reflow won’t happen for the document (:root) if we don’t force a reflow at the body level. As a consequence, we’re using the --RS__maxLineLength CSS variable to force this reflow and slightly alter its value whenever needed e.g. “pagination to scroll” in vertical writing, mix-blend-mode in sepia mode, “number of columns” user setting, etc.

This will recalc the body’s max-width, causing a reflow which will propagate to the column layout we set for :root.

Notorious limitations

When the spec was published, the Financial Times immediately switched to its own JavaScript implementation for the following reasons:

configurable column widths, gutters and margins;
better handling of position: absolute || fixed;
support of column-span: <integer>;
better fragmentation (column breaks);
grouping of columns into pages;
enforce a baseline grid;
better handling of box-shadow and outline.

As far as we can tell, this implementation might create some issues, especially when it comes to a11y because it duplicates and hides part of elements to manage fragmentation.

Notes

It is our understanding the Opera implementation of overflow: -o-paged-x in Presto solved most of the spec’s limitations, as listed by the Financial Times:

position: fixed || absolute;
fragmentation;
column-span: integer;
overflow, by switching to paged media;
implementing CSS figures as a bonus.

It is important to note the spec has been republished as a Working Draft. It is very unlikely a level 2 spec will tackle those problems in the short term.

From experience, we can also report there tends to be implementation-specific bugs with newer layout specs e.g. flexbox, grid, etc.

Missing pieces

There are several shortcomings we must deal with:

the column-gap applies to adjacent column boxes, but there is nothing to set a columns-start-margin and columns-end-margin: this is particularly problematic when columns are set at the :root level and overflow;
there is no JavaScript API available, we don’t even know the number of columns which have been created and their real width;
since we can’t use overflow: paged-x, there is no way we can force the scrollWidth to be a multiple of the viewport, we must force the creation of an extra column if needed.
the lack of “column queries” makes it really difficult for authors to do responsive design.

Reading Systems Requirements for reflowable text

[Implementers’ doc] [Authors’ doc]

Source: EPUB Content Documents 3.2

There’s a few criteria Reading Systems must meet in order to be conformant:

it must support the official definition of CSS as described in the W3C CSS Snapshot;
it must support all -epub- prefixed properties (list).

In addition:

it should support all applicable modules in CSS Snapshot which have reached at least Candidate Recommendation status and are widely implemented;
its user agent stylesheet should support HTML Suggested Rendering;
it should respect authors CSS and user styles as defined in Reading System overrides.

CSS Snapshot

Since we’re relying on web browsers’ rendering engine and web views, this should not be an issue. Our main concern should be future-proofing Readium CSS to stay up-to-date with current/modern CSS authoring (cf. issue #12)

Prefixed properties

Blink and Webkit rendering engines may support some but it is unclear how we can be 100% conformant there, as it would require parsing the CSS to replace -epub-properties with the standard ones if the author has not used them.

As a matter of fact,

Authors are advised to use CSS-native solutions for the removed properties where and when they are available.

and,

Authors currently using these prefixed properties are advised to move to unprefixed versions as soon as support allows.

Proposal: let the rendering engine/web view deal with this. We don’t have Houdini yet and parsing CSS is a heavy process altering performance pretty badly.

HTML Suggested Rendering

We made sure we can rely on UA Stylesheets and have created a patch for paged views.

The patch deals with:

fragmentation (widows, orphans, page breaks);
hyphenation;
open type features;
borders;
horizontal spacing;
little normalization between UA stylesheets.

It doesn’t change the nature of HTML Suggested Rendering though, it only builds on it for EPUB rendering (adjustments).

Reading System Overrides

What’s important:

users should be able to override authors’ styles as desired;
reading systems should not override authors’ styles unless strictly necessary, in a way that preserves the Cascade.

We meet both requirements by default.

As regards the cascade, the following list is the priority order we should emulate:

important user agent declarations;
important user declarations;
important author declarations;
normal author declarations;
normal user declarations;
normal user agent declarations.

Most user declarations have to use !important to make sure they are applied, which is conformant. However, we try to manage “normal author declarations” by carefully targeting selectors for each user setting.

Few user agent declarations have to use !important as well, in order to make sure the EPUB file displays as expected (pagination, page margins, etc.). In other words, those overrides are strictly necessary.

Please make sure to check the “CSS User Setting Recommendations” and “Stylesheets Order” to manage overrides as best as possible.

Notes

A conformant author’s stylesheet must not:

use the direction property;
use the unicode-bidi property.

How to use CSS custom properties (a.k.a. variables)

[Implementers’ doc]

Note: CSS variables are not and won’t be supported in IE11. You can either create a static stylesheet for all UA browsers or decide to leverage them in most UA browsers + use a JS fallback for IE11 if you want to support this browser – you can test for CSS variables support in JS.

What are CSS variables?

CSS variables allow an author to assign arbitrary values to a property with an author-chosen name. This custom property must start with --. The var() function then allows the author to use those values elsewhere in the document.

:root { 
	--primaryColor: red; 
}

a { 
	color: var(--primaryColor); 
}

button { 
	color: white; 
	background-color: var(--primaryColor); 
}

If you’re familiar with CSS pre-processors (LESS, SASS, Stylus, etc.), you’re probably using variables already. The major difference is that CSS variables are supported in the browser and, consequently, you can access and edit them in real-time using JavaScript.

Global references:

CSS Custom Properties spec
Can I Use
CSS Variables: Why should you care — developers.google.com
CSS Custom Properties in Microsoft Edge
PostCSS plugin to transform CSS variables into a static representation
JS Perf — CSS Variables vs. Inline Styles
CSS Variables are a game changer

Cascade and inheritance

Custom properties follow standard cascading rules. In other words, you can define the same property at different levels of specificity.

:root { 
	--fontSize: 16px; 
} 

aside { 
	--fontSize: 12px; 
} 

body, aside { 
	font-size: var(--fontSize); 
	/* Will be 16px for body and 12px for aside */ 
}

You can also use them in media queries.

:root { 
	--defaultFontSize: 16px; 
} 

@media screen and (max-width: 560px) { 
	:root { 
		--defaultFontSize: 14px; 
	} 
} 

html { 
	font-size: var(--defaultFontSize); 
	/* Will be 14px if the viewport max-width < 560px and 16px otherwise */ 
}

To sum things up, variables bring a lot of flexibility and customization to CSS. It can also simplify your stylesheets and make them much more maintainable.

Fallback

In case you want to use them, you’ll have to hardcode values for IE11 (and Edge 14).

:root {
	--primaryColor: red; 
} 

a { 
	color: red; /* Fallback */ 
	color: var(--primaryColor); 
} 

button { 
	color: white; 
	background-color: red; /* Fallback */ 
	background-color: var(--primaryColor); 
}

That could be managed via JavaScript though, so that you don’t need to maintain fallbacks in pure CSS.

It is important to note the var() function provides a fallback mechanism itself, in case your custom property is not set.

The function looks like this:

var(<custom-property-name> [, <declaration-value> ]? )

:root {
	/* No --primaryColor in there */ 
} 

a { 
	color: var(--primaryColor, red); /* In which red is the fallback */ 
} 

button { 
	color: white; 
	background-color: var(--primaryColor, red); /* In which red is the fallback */ 
}

That could be useful for theming for instance, by setting default values as fallbacks then declaring custom properties using JavaScript.

Although browsers have been optimized to deal with CSS variables, please note performance might suffer in some browsers if you have a lot of variables with a fallback.

Using CSS variables in JavaScript

Feature detect

As seen in this article by Michael Scharnagl, if you want to test for support, you can do the following:

if (window.CSS && window.CSS.supports && window.CSS.supports('--a', 0)) { 
	// CSS custom properties supported. 
} else { 
	// CSS custom properties not supported 
}

Since CSS feature queries are not supported by IE11, the previous snippet will return false.

It will return true for browsers which support feature queries since @supports only checks if the syntax is correct (and don’t bother checking if the custom property exists).

Retrieve values

You can retrieve values by using getPropertyValue("--name_of_the_variable") (it is a computed style).

var myColor = window.getComputedStyle(document.documentElement).getPropertyValue("--textColor");

Set values

You can set values by using setProperty("--name_of_the_variable", "value").

document.documentElement.style.setProperty("--textColor", "#000");

If you’re appending a style element in the head of the document, you can also change the value in there, especially if you have a lot of elements to manage. For instance, if a --maxImageHeight variable is defined in the CSS for img, you could do the following:

var newStyles = document.createElement('style'); 
newStyles.id = "overrides"; 
var docHeight = window.getComputedStyle(document.body).getPropertyValue("height") + "px"; 
var newMaxImageHeight = document.createTextNode("img {--maxImageHeight: " + docHeight + ";}");
newStyles.appendChild(newMaxImageHeight); 
document.head.appendChild(newStyles);

This will override the value in the original CSS since the img selector is more specific. It is important to notice you could hardcode styles here for browsers which don’t support variables (adding max-height: docHeight to the textNode you’re appending in the stylesheet).

Interesting hacks

CSS variables offer a lot of flexibility.

Avoid JS concatenation

As seen in this article by Zack Bloom, if you want to avoid managing concatenation (value + unit) in JavaScript, you could use the calc() function in CSS.

.element { 
	height: calc(var(--element-height) * 1px); 
}

Testing active breakpoints

As seen in this article by Eric Ponto, you could create a --breakpoint variable to “emulate” something like container/element queries.

body { 
	--breakpoint: medium; 
} 

@media screen and (max-width: 30em) { 
	body { 
		--breakpoint: small; 
	} 
} 

@media screen and (min-width: 50em) { 
	body { 
		--breakpoint: large; 
	} 
}

Then create a function to return the breakpoint and append styles accordingly.

You could probably leverage such a hack to implement some kind of column-width media query in paged view, but it would require CSS authors to provide specific stylesheets with this non-standard media as a link attribute – otherwise, performance will be really really bad as you would have to hijack the entire stylesheet to retrieve media queries first.

Setting another variable as a value

As seen in the developers.google.com article, you can set the value of the variable to refer to another variable at runtime by using the var() function in your call to setProperty().

document.documentElement.style.setProperty("--primary-color", "var(--secondary-color)");

Abusing CSS variables to make them read and acted on by JavaScript

As seen in the spec itself (example 3), you could create values which sole purpose is to be read and acted on by JavaScript.

While the following variable would obviously be useless as a variable (invalid value):

--foo: if(x > 5) this.width = 10;

You could use it in JavaScript since it’s still a valid custom property.

User themes

You could even go the extra mile and provide an “import theme” feature or implement custom styles inputs (color pickers, font family, etc.) in the UI so that users can create their own theme on the fly, then manage it more easily (storing the user theme as a style element with an id in localStorage for instance).

See this CSS-Tricks’ article for use cases and demos.

User Settings, Reading Modes and Themes

[Implementers’ doc] [Authors’ info]

The idea is:

appending/removing flags and CSS variables for user settings (inline style on html);
managing user settings entirely via CSS so that we don’t need to manipulate the DOM too much.

There are alternatives approaches you can adopt if this one doesn’t fit.

Note: Possible values are strict i.e. implementers can’t use any other value; recommended values are loose i.e. they are left to implementers’ judgment.

Mechanism for user settings

The ReadiumCSS-after.css stylesheet, which contains user settings, can be appended before runtime; its declarations won’t be applied until user variables are set.

User settings require the following process:

add the flag and its value to html when applicable (font override, font size and/or advanced setting);
add the setting-specific variable and its value to html;
styles are updated live.

The selectors used in user settings are indeed “conditional”, styles are applied if the variable (or a specific value for reading modes) is set as an inline style in html (:root).

Setting and removing a variable

Setting

var root = document.documentElement; 
root.style.setProperty("name of var", "value");

You don’t need to remove the variable before setting another value, the new value will simply override the existing one.

Removing

You can either remove the style explicitly with removeProperty():

var root = document.documentElement; 
root.style.removeProperty("name of var");

Or implicitly by using an empty string as a value with setProperty():

var root = document.documentElement; 
root.style.setProperty("name of var", "");

Setting a property with an empty string as the value will indeed invoke removeProperty(), as defined in the CSS Object Model Spec.

Flags

Some variables behave like flags. You could also use custom data-* attributes or CSS classes to manage the following ones. See the “Quickstart” doc for customization.

By default, those flags are not set. Then their initialization depends on your user settings’ management e.g. apply user settings to all EPUBs, only the ones that have already been customized, etc.

User view

Allows to switch between paged and scroll view.

--USER__view

Supported values: readium-paged-on | readium-scroll-on

Override class: Chrome (should be applied by any means necessary)

If the flag is not set, ReadiumCSS will fall back to the paged view.

Font Family override

Acts as an explicit switch to override the publisher’s font-family.

--USER__fontOverride

Supported value: readium-font-on

Override class: None. This flag is required to change the font-family user setting.

To switch back to the publisher’s font, you can either set an empty string as a value or remove the property.

Advanced Settings

Acts as an explicit switch to override the publisher’s styles.

If you provide users with a “Publisher’s styles” toggle, it must be enabled and disabled accordingly.

--USER__advancedSettings

Supported value: readium-advanced-on

Override class: None. This flag is required to apply the font-family, the font-size and/or advanced user settings.

To switch back to the publisher’s styles, you can either set an empty string as a value or remove the property. This will disable all advanced settings requiring the flag.

Reading Modes

We currently have two reading modes for night and sepia.

--USER__appearance

Supported values: readium-day-on | readium-sepia-on | readium-night-on

Override class: Chrome (should be applied by any means necessary)

If the flag is not set, ReadiumCSS will fall back to the day mode.

Filters

Please note night mode provides two extra specific variables:

--USER__darkenFilter

Supported value: readium-darken-on

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To disable the filter, you can either set an empty string as a value or remove the property.

--USER__invertFilter

Supported value: readium-invert-on

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To disable the filter, you can either set an empty string as a value or remove the property.

Accessibility Normalization

Users may want to normalize text (no bold, no italics, etc.) for accessibility reasons, using a non a11y-specific typeface.

--USER__a11yNormalize

Supported value: readium-a11y-on

Required flag: --USER__fontOverride: readium-font-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To disable the normalization, you can either set an empty string as a value or remove the property.

List of variables

Layout

The user can set the number of columns and page margins.

Number of columns

--USER__colCount

Possible values: 1 | 2 | auto (default)

Required flag: none

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To reset, change the value to auto.

By default, this setting behaves as an auto value, it will switch to 1 or 2 columns depending on the minimum width available and font-size.

It is up to implementers to decide whether they want this setting to be available and override any configuration or only some (e.g. setting only available in landscape and/or larger screens).

Page margins

--USER__pageMargins

Recommended values: a range from 0.5 to 2. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: none

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To reset, change the value to 1.

The user margins are a factor of the reference we set.

This will probably be fine-tuned in the next version (beta).

Themes (background and text colors)

The user can set a background-color and color.

The following two variables must be used together.

--USER__backgroundColor --USER__textColor

Possible values: Color HEX (e.g. #FFFFFF), rgb(a), hsl.

Required flag: none

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To reset, remove both variables.

Hyphenation and justification

The user can set text-align and hyphens for body copy contents.

Text align

--USER__textAlign

Possible values: left (LTR) or right (RTL) | justify

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Note: the value start can be used to let all rendering engines, excepted Trident (IE11) and EdgeHTML (Edge), automatically deal with left and right based on the direction (dir attribute) set for the document and its nested elements.

Hyphens

--USER__bodyHyphens

Possible Values: auto | none

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Warning: for the time being, automatic hyphenation won’t work if you are using the Blink rendering engine (either via Chrome or a Webview, including Electron’s) on ChromeOS, Linux and Windows. It indeed is not implemented yet and we recommend not trying to polyfill it using JavaScript as it will create a11y issues, especially with screen readers.

As a consequence, we strongly advise implementers against providing users with an hyphenation-specific setting if targeting this rendering engine.

Typography

The user can set font-family, font-size and line-height for body copy contents.

Font family

--USER__fontFamily

Possible values: var(--RS__oldStyleTf) | var(--RS__modernTf) | var(--RS__sansTf) | var(--RS__humanistTf) | <string>

For Japanese, possible values become: var(--RS__serif-ja) (horizontal writing) | var(--RS__sans-serif-ja) (horizontal writing) | var(--RS__serif-ja-v) (vertical writing) | var(--RS__sans-serif-ja-v) (vertical writing) | <string>

Required flag: --USER__fontOverride: readium-font-on

Override class: User settings (should be applied by any means necessary)

To reset, remove the required flag.

Font size

We have to normalize font-size for body copy elements so that it can work in pure CSS. In order to do so, we are using a normalize. The --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on inline style must be set for html in order for the font-size setting to work.

Although it might be an issue to authors at first sight, this approach is backed by actual data.

--USER__fontSize

Recommended values: a range from 75% to 250%. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings (should be applied by any means necessary)

Type scale

If the --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on style is set for html, you can customize the font-size of all elements using a factor. This may come in handy on mobile devices, if the user sets a large font-size.

--USER__typeScale

Possible values: 1 | 1.067 | 1.125 | 1.2 (suggested default) | 1.25 | 1.333 | 1.414 | 1.5 | 1.618

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

You can use different type scale values depending on the font-size. For instance, if the user sets a large one, you might want to decrease the type scale so that headings are not super large.

Line height

--USER__lineHeight

Recommended values: a range from 1 to 2. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Paragraphs’ formatting

The user can set margin-top, margin-bottom and text-indent for paragraphs.

Paragraphs’ spacing

--USER__paraSpacing

Recommended values: a range from 0 to 2rem. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Paragraphs’ indent

--USER__paraIndent

Recommended values: a range from 0 to 3rem. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Characters’ spacing

The user can set word-spacing and letter-spacing for headings and body copy contents.

Word spacing

--USER__wordSpacing

Recommended values: a range from 0 to 1rem. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Letter spacing

--USER__letterSpacing

Recommended values: a range from 0 to 0.5rem. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Arabic Ligatures

--USER__ligatures

Possible values: none | common-ligatures

Required flag: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Themes

In this model, themes are just a set of user variables with specific values.

It becomes even easier to override them for the user as the values are already user settings.

In other words, think of preset and custom themes as a set of variables, which makes it easier to create, manipulate and cache them.

Alternative options

There is not a lot of alternatives when it comes to managing user settings. Options include:

appending/removing stylesheets (either link or style element) dynamically;
traversing the DOM and appending inline styles using JavaScript;
using classes or custom attributes for a limited subset of settings (e.g. reading modes);
leveraging native features web views have to offer.

Please bear in mind Readium CSS provides a baseline, it resonably manages all those issues using CSS only. But if you want to offer users the most advanced experience there can be, you’ll end up with a mix of all those options.

For instance, you can’t really manage text-align perfectly if you don’t traverse the DOM to find elements for which the user setting should not apply, CSS has no way to retrieve those elements.

It is worth mentioning that at least some rendering engines are optimized to manage global CSS variables (i.e. the ones declared in :root) and reserve a special cache for faster lookup and updates. Changes should consequently be handled as inline styles in the html element if you want the best performance possible.

User settings can be language-specific

It is important to note that the list of user settings you may provide users with can change depending on the primary language of the publication.

Indeed, it doesn’t make sense to have some user settings in some languages, and they would do more harm than good e.g. hyphens in CJK. Ideally, those settings should therefore be removed from the UI, or at least disabled, if needed.

All languages other than Latin

Implementers will need to load different list of fonts based on the languages listed in Default Fonts.

The most complex issue is finding fonts for those languages, especially as mobile systems often ship with the minimum amount of fonts possible to support Indic, Arabic, Hebrew, CJK, etc. And when the platform provides an extended selection, users often have to download them beforehand.

The following is provided as guidance only:

the app should at least offer the publisher’s font and the default (var(--RS__baseFontFamily)) for the language – which should work automatically if the correct language is set for each document;
if implementers want to extend the list:
use pre-installed fonts if the system offers some;
use downloadable fonts if the system offers some;
carefully pick fonts supporting the language and the idiosyncrasies of its typography;
fall back to Google Noto Fonts.
users probably have fonts already installed, re-use those fonts if possible (advanced setting in which they can access or declare those fonts).

Right to left scripts

User settings to disable are:

--USER__bodyHyphens;
--USER__wordSpacing;
--USER__letterSpacing.

User settings to add are:

--USER__ligatures.

CJK

For Chinese, Japanese, and Korean, implementers must manage both horizontal and vertical writing modes, since the pagination model differs.

Horizontal writing mode

User settings to disable are:

--USER__textAlign;
--USER__bodyHyphens;
--USER__paraIndent;
--USER__wordSpacing;
--USER__letterSpacing.

Vertical writing mode

This also impacts the Mongolian script.

User settings to disable are:

--USER__colCount;
--USER__textAlign;
--USER__bodyHyphens;
--USER__paraIndent;
--USER__wordSpacing;
--USER__letterSpacing.

Baseline for a11y-related user settings

[Implementers’ doc] [Authors’ info]

Our current baseline for user settings includes:

night/sepia modes, and custom background-color and color;
text-align and hyphens;
font-size and line-height;
a11y-related typefaces;
letter- and word-spacing;
removing italics, subscrips and superscripts, and drop caps.

We should probably consider additional options:

forcing an outline for focused elements;
unfloating elements;
removing images.

Please note some or all of those settings may be added in Readium CSS at some point.

A few notes:

The a11y-related typefaces are not necessarily typefaces which were specifically designed for a11y. A typeface a reader is used to, like Verdana, Trebuchet, etc., can be a11y-related as well. From research, the more varied typefaces available, the better. There is no silver bullet there, some people don’t like Open Dyslexic for instance, and prefer sans-serif typefaces they are used to.

Removing italics, subs and sups, drop caps and floated elements should probably be automatic if the typeface or theme selected was explicitly designed for dyslexia. Additionnaly, the --USER__a11yNormalize: readium-a11y-on flag is available and bring this feature to other typefaces.

OS settings

Some Operating Systems provide users with global settings. We must take those settings into account, which is the purpose of the “OS a11y” module. This module still needs some improvements.

We’ll have to make decisions about reading modes there: if the user sets the monochrome option, how are we supposed to deal with sepia and colors? If the user sets an inverted high-contrast mode, what happens in night mode? There can indeed be multiple users for the same computer, using the same account, and we should cover this case out of the box.

Current a11y Features on the market

There are features you might want to add to your Reading System so that it can cover the needs of all readers.

Readium CSS can help but can’t manage all of those features. Indeed, CSS might fall short of your expectations, especially on reliability. In other words, CSS is not necessarily the best way to manage features which could be considered in its scope at first sight.

As a rule, CSS can be used for styling (colors, highlights, etc.) but can’t be used to target contents (text nodes) directly. As a consequence, you’ll need to add hooks in the DOM (extra markup, classes, attributes, etc.) for some features.

Dyslexia

Luc Maumet (EDRLab) has conducted an analysis on the features available in dedicated software. Here are the features Readium CSS can manage and those it can’t.

Features in Readium CSS Scope

Create and personalize a profile (customizable theme which can be saved and retrieved)
Add space between words
Add space between letters
Change the typeface
Offer a dyslexia typeface
Change the font-size
Improve line-height

Features outscoping Readium CSS

Alternate colors for words
Alternate colors for lines
Highlight a specific letter
Highlight uppercase letters
Highlight punctuation
Highlight syllabes
Highlight consonants and vowels with different colors
Text to Speech
Highlight a specific sound in the text
Export contents with the customized layout

Vestibular disorders

There’s an a11y “issue” which is quite unknown, but may impact a lot of people, either temporarily or permanently: vestibular disorders.

To put it simply, some interactions can make the user dizzy, uneasy, and in some cases ruin her/his entire day, because the user feels like they can’t keep balance when walking or even staying up, or feel vertigo. See this article for further details and illustrations.

At the very minimum, allow the user to disable animations which may create effects (e.g. page-transition animation). But everything else will vary from implementation to implementation.

On iOS/Mac, there’s a system setting which has been implemented and browsers increasingly support the prefers-reduced-motion media query to design accordingly.

There’s little we can do about interactive EPUB contents themselves, but we can at least promote what Mozilla got wonderfully right from the start to authors, i.e. an overlay asking users to set their preference.

Internationalization

Very little information on a11y is currently available in the W3C Text Layout and Typography Requirements.

All we know at the moment is that, in the Arabic and Farsi scripts, disabling ligatures might help for dyslexia.

User preferences’ insights

[Implementers’ info] [Authors’ info] [WIP]

In case you don’t have solid data related to user preferences, here is some information to help you kickstart your UX.

It is worth noting this should not be considered a guide, this is just a list of interesting observations, notes and remarks. UX research is critical and there’s not a lot available for ebooks so far, so you’ll have to do it yourself to see what works and what doesn’t.

This is really tricky as there may be a cultural factor to take into account. In our research, results varied significantly from one market to another. Unfortunately, it is impossible to tell how important this cultural factor is compared to others. In other words, if you’re going global, it might be interesting to do some specific research on this.

User Settings

When asked directly, the vast majority of users will say they prefer basic settings (reading modes, typeface, and font size) over other options (maximum amount of settings possible, themes, customizable themes). Customizable themes and advanced settings are equally popular, at a distant second place.

Once again, this is a complex UX issue and your mileage may vary. On Android for instance, there is a lot of apps with advanced settings as the default, and millions of people are using them daily. So it’s primarily about your UX proposal, people using it, etc.

Hopefully, Readium CSS was designed to take all those options into account: modules are take or leave, which implies you can build any UX from them.

Typography

We’ve been running forms on this topic but answers can’t be taken at face value since they might well be biased – given the eprdctn and a11y communities on social networks, and the probable tech-savyness of people who came across those forms in the first place; what is the most interesting is the open-ended questions and how you can interpret them.

People change the publisher’s typeface

People keeping the publisher’s typeface are in the minority (< 15%). Most users at least change the typeface occasionally (see reasons below), although they don’t necessarily do it for each ebook – some ebooks simply use the default typeface so it’s quite complex to measure.

What’s important is that you’d better have some kind of bulletproof selection of RS typefaces. “Bulletproof” is the keyword here, since it is difficult to imagine a selection that will satisfy everybody. There won’t be any silver bullet.

Since more people systematically change the publisher’s typeface than those who never do it, implementers might end up with a huge share of users systematically changing the typeface and could adjust the UX accordingly (global setting applying the typeface in all books).

It also implies you’d better have fonts providing with the largest characters set possible.

Why do people change the typeface?

Legibility. We’re including dyslexia typefaces since it is kind of related to this issue.

In some way, this justifies we must change the typeface for (at least) body copy by any means necessary – and absolutely everything for dys.

As an aside, respondents didn’t hesitate to criticize the publisher/graphic designer when they feel they made an abysmal choice of typeface(s). Please pick the typefaces you want to provide carefully. There can be language subtleties to take into account, and pairs, ligatures, kerning, etc. might have been done well for one latin language but not other latin languages for instance – especially when those other languages are using diacritics.

Other reasons were given, the most interesting ones being:

trying new fonts for fun: maybe you can find some way to leverage the fun factor, by implementing a little game to teach typography fundamentals or something like this, it is usually a good idea to leverage the fun factor since it will put the user in a super good mood (UX);
mood i.e. some pick a typeface that fits the mood of the publication;
on the one hand, consistency i.e. all ebooks have the same typeface;
on the other hand, breaking the monotony i.e. changing the typeface for each book.

Typefaces that should be included in a reading app

Users can be gathered in diverse categories.

The Minimalists

They don’t want an awful lot of fonts, they want the best option possible for serif and sans-serif, which means typefaces of outstanding quality (good legibility, perfect kerning, OpenType Features, etc.).

The Defaulters

Arial, Georgia, Verdana, Calibri, Times (New Roman), Segoe UI…

In other words, the fonts they find and use in MS Word.

On a related note, The defaults for Kindle (Bookerly) and Play Books (Literata) have become pretty popular. It is worth noting these custom fonts were commissioned, and it could be an alternative if you can afford it.

The eInkers

Basically, you’re given a list of typefaces you can find on a Kobo, Pocketbook or Kindle. This might primarily impact some companies doing both eInk Readers and apps but there could well be a possibility to make the user feel “at home” there, by having a few of those typefaces as well.

The Slabs

Cæcilia seems to be one of the must-haves, and it’s a slab serif, so you might want to at least provide one in this category or even a lookalike.

The Librists

Those ones are more interested in libre/open source fonts you can find at Google Fonts, Font Squirrel, Github, SIL, etc. More on that later.

Answers include Merriweather, Bitter (slab), Vollkorn, Gentium, Ubuntu, Lato, etc.

The A11ys

Unsurprisingly, you’ll need a11y-related fonts: Open Dyslexic is a popular one, but other fonts cited in dyslexia guidelines are mentioned as well (Verdana, Trebuchet, Comic Sans, etc.).

The Printers

Some people would like to have typefaces like Garamond, Bembo, Baskerville, Times New Roman, etc. Some respondents explained that they wanted the ebook to be more like a print book.

It is important to note that their screen rendering can be utterly terrible (cf. what Steve Matteson has to say about Times New Roman on screen). A lot has changed in designing typefaces for the screen since they were digitized and reworked versions may be available.

The Full Metal Typographers

To sum things up, they want all the fonts the platform has to offer, which means all system and locally-installed fonts.

With the advancement of Open Type Features, some issues may arise though: stylesets are unreliable, all fonts don’t manage features the same way e.g. subs, sups, ordinal, or diagonal-fraction, etc. This applies anyways, but could become especially complex if the user can access all the fonts available on the platform.

A few remarks there:

if you’re reading between the lines, you’ll see people list typefaces they’re used to – this is kind of obvious in Literata/Bookerly –, so you’d better focus on their category, traits and personality, which implies lookalikes/alternatives could do as well;
if you want to meet the Printers’ demand, you should check the modern versions of those fonts first, as they have been fine-tuned for screen rendering and can offer a lot more legibility (cf. Linotype’s eText collection);
you could bet on a flagship typeface like Amazon & Google but that’s a huge investment (custom typeface);
you’d better be cautious about OTF as soon as possible since the user may find itself with some weird results: letters and numbers as ordinal, decorative glyphs replacing the latin alphabet as the typeface designer used stylesets for this, etc.

Installing extra fonts

It actually is a thing.

Once again, there may be a huge bias there (tech-savvy users), but we were surprised to find out that not only respondents would be willing to install extra fonts, quite a significant number is already doing it. Think of users installing fonts on their eReaders for instance.

However, that opens the possibility to manage/install extra fonts. The major source of custom fonts seems to be Google Fonts for respondents but others go the extra mile and install licensed fonts locally, in which case they might want access to all the fonts installed on the system.

You’d better be cautious about Google Fonts as they are often a few versions behind, and the typeface designer could have added support for extra languages, OpenType Features, etc.

This obviously is a feature requiring some extra work, and some platforms may impose limitations, so it should just be considered an interesting piece of information.

An important note: some users had to install a font for a11y purposes (e.g. dyslexia) so it’s important you meet this requirement out of the box so that they don’t have to take that extra step.

Internationalization

[Implementers’ doc] [Authors’ doc] [WIP]

The aim of this document is to provide implementers with a baseline for internationalization.

The current situation

Internationalization is an ongoing process, with browsers offering subpar interoperability (typography, writing modes, etc.), Operating Systems sometimes lacking fonts for some languages, and documentation providing little information on topics of interest to Reading Systems (a11y, settings, etc.).

This could well explain why the most popular Reading Apps tend to implement the least common denominator for all languages, especially when it comes to user settings, and to not support more complex languages implementers either know they can’t support well or are used on smaller markets the app/service is not targeting.

Occasionally, when an app does support a language, it can put some constraints on authors, as there is no other way to make sure the publication will be handled well otherwise e.g. specifying the Hans or Hant script for Chinese (zh).

We can’t overemphasize the importance of the internationalization process though, as the 24 languages we added extend support to 3,049,150,507 speakers, from the 1,150 people speaking Western Canadian Inuktitut, to the 1,200,000,000 speaking Chinese. Implementing right to left scripts will extend support to 411,000,000 native speakers, while vertical writing to at least 130,200,000 – excluding Chinese and Korean.

In total, we can cover the needs of 5,262,900,507 speakers. Credit where credit is due, this wouldn’t have been possible if Operating Systems and browsers didn’t tackle this process upstream, added fonts for those languages and improved support in rendering engines.

Resources

W3C Internationalization Working Group Home Page
Creating HTML Pages in Arabic, Hebrew and Other Right-to-left Scripts (tutorial)
Styling vertical Chinese, Japanese, Korean and Mongolian text
International text layout and typography index
Requirements for Japanese Text Layout
Requirements for Chinese Text Layout
Requirements for Hangul Text Layout
Requirements for the Arabic Script
Requirements for Hebrew Text Layout
Requirements for Indic Text Layout
EBPAJ File creation guide

What implementers need

Supporting the maximum amount of languages and scripts is a complex process.

As a consequence, work for internationalization should be tackled early, as the changes and adaptations needed will have a significant impact on an existing implementation. It indeed impacts the entire implementation, and not only CSS.

Retrieving the significant information in the OPF

Implementers will need a way to retrieve page-progression-direction and the primary language (<dc:language>) of the publication.

Page-progression-direction

This attribute is set on the <spine> item, and the value rtl should be considered important information for the whole process.

This value signals the publication is either an RTL script, or is using the vertical-rl writing mode, which is the reason why we must find the primary language of the publication next.

The value is important to store, as it will be the one used for the dir attribute to append if it is missing in a document.

Primary Language

It is very important to note the primary language must be checked in all cases, and not only when the page-progression-direction is set or has an rtl value.

Indeed, this piece will be even more critical in the following steps, as it will trigger the list of fonts to load for the publication, the user settings to provide, and the xml:lang attribute to append if it is missing in a document.

Possible issues

The OPF file should not be considered a single source of truth for the publication, since issues may arise relatively quickly. We can’t call the process “heuristics” per se, it’s more of a chain of educated guesses.

Multiple language items

There exists an increasing corpus of EPUB files with multiple <dc:language> items. Some authoring tools, for instance, list all languages a publication contains.

In this case, page-progression-direction should serve as a hint, if present. For instance:

the first <dc:language> item is English;
the second <dc:language> item is Japanese;
the page-progression-direction is rtl;
the primary language is Japanese.

Obviously, this can quickly become an issue if both languages share the same page-progression-direction…

the first <dc:language> item is English;
the second <dc:language> item is Japanese;
the page-progression-direction is missing;
we can’t guess the primary language from the OPF.

In such an edge case, to achieve the best interoperability possible, the first <dc:language> element must be considered the primary language, unless you can pre-process all documents in a publication to determine it beforehand.

Missing page-progression-direction

For some reason the page-progression-direction may be missing in the OPF, which can be true if the publication is EPUB2 for instance – which supports the direction CSS property and, in theory, could support RTL scripts.

The following guidance is informal:

if the page-progression-direction is missing;
if there is only one <dc:language> item which clearly signals the page-progression-direction:

ar, fa, and he;
zh-Hant, or zh-TW.

then you can assume the page-progression-direction is rtl.

The decision to handle this edge case is up to each implementer, especially as it can be considered a patch of an authoring failure.

Triggering the correct page-progression-direction

Once the page-progression-direction is defined as rtl, it must be reversed in the app:

the previous resource (document) is on the right;
the next resource (document) is on the left.

Navigating the publication should follow this pattern.

Appending information into documents

Missing attributes in each document is far from an uncommon or edge case.

Since the page-progression-direction or <dc:language> are already set in the OPF, some authors might think they will automatically apply to all the resources in the EPUB file, and explicitly set it only when it differs from those global values. More importantly, some Reading Apps are automatically managing this, and should authors only check their files in those apps, it could lead them to believe it just works.

Language

The language is important as it will enable hyphenation and use the proper rules specific to each language if a dictionnary is available, change the default typeface for some languages, and even apply language-specific styles for layout (e.g. pagination, defaults for unstyled publications, etc.).

The following process must be implemented:

if xml:lang can’t be found on html;
check if xml:lang can be found on body, copy and set it to html, and stop there if it is;
if it can’t be found on body, use the primary language retrieved from the OPF file and set it to html and body.

Direction

The dir attribute is critical too, as it will reverse the column direction for RTL scripts.

The following must only apply if the primary language is ar, fa, and he. It MUST NOT apply to CJK.

The following process must be implemented:

if the dir attribute can’t be found on html;
check if dir can be found on body:

if it is the same value as the one retrieved from the OPF file, copy it;
if it differs from the one retrieved from the OPF file, change the value;

set the dir attribute with the correct value on html.

Loading the correct styles

Readium CSS provides implementers with specific stylesheets for RTL scripts and CJK (including the Mongolian script), those styles must be loaded accordingly. Otherwise, styles for LTR scripts in the horizontal writing mode will apply.

Guidance can be found in the Injection and Pagination document.

Modifying the UI of the app

Ideally, several parts of the app should be customizable depending on the publication. Another option is implementing the least common denominator for all languages.

All Languages

The list of fonts the app offers to users should be specific to the primary language of the publication, and writing-mode if it applies – Japanese currently.

This means fonts for Latin language can’t be reused for Indic, RTL scripts, CJK, etc.

RTL

Several parts of the UI must follow the direction (rtl) of the primary language:

the running header (title of the publication or chapter);
the toc and its entries;
user settings e.g. text align;
implementers might want to localize the interface based on the language set at the system level, or at least fall back to English.

Moreover, some user settings should be removed if used (letter- and word-spacing) and another one added (arabic ligatures in ar and fa).

CJK

Although the UI can keep an ltr direction with a horizontal-tb writing mode, some extra attention should be paid:

make sure the “UI font” can display the characters needed in those languages;
implementers might want to allow authors to set a vertical-* writing mode for the navigation document (nav.xhtml);
implementers might want to localize the interface based on the language set at the system level, or at least fall back to English.

Moreover, some user settings should be removed if used (text-align, hyphens, letter- and word-spacing, number of columns in vertical writing, etc.). See User Prefs for further details.

Internationalize features

Implementers should make sure features like search, highlighting, etc. can work well with bidirectional text and unicode – CJK, especially as some characters change from horizontal to vertical writing modes.

Another issue to take into account is that input methods might not allow users to use some features easily, in which case extended research should be made to check realistic options.

Fonts

Implementers should make sure they offer at least two options: the publisher’s font and the default. If they want to extend the list of fonts they provide for some languages, they should follow guidance in the User Preferences doc.

How authors can help

Authors can help in different ways, from authoring files to giving valuable information we can use to improve the entire Readium CSS project.

Authoring

In some cases, EPUB files themselves will help us improve support tremendously.

The metadata in the OPF file will help us trigger the expected behavior. For instance:

declaring only one <dc:language> will help us determine the primary language of the publication;
if this is not possible, add the primary language as the first <dc:language> item in the OPF;
declaring the script e.g. zh-Hant or mn-Mong will help us trigger the correct writing-mode;
using the EBPAJ guide meta will help us improve support across platforms.

Setting attributes in each document of the publication will also help us make educated choices and could eventually allow us to handle some edge cases like mixed directions or mixed writing modes. Our aim is obviously not to put the burden on authors there, but collaboration is the only solution to get around those edge cases the EPUB specification doesn’t discuss.

What you can do:

embed fonts when necessary, so that users have at least two options to choose from in settings and/or proper support of the language;
set the xml:lang attribute on html;
set the dir attribute on html;
avoid using the direction CSS property, as it is now recommended.

Reporting issues

First and foremost, please be assured that we’re as annoyed as you are if there is an issue. It doesn’t mean we don’t care, far from it… it just means we lacked information or misunderstood some requirements when designing Readium CSS. Our goal is to achieve the best support possible, and we know we can’t fulfill it without your expertise.

If you encounter any issue specific to a language or script, do not hesitate to open a new issue in the github repository. A reduced sample will definitely help. Check our guidelines for further details.

The most information we have, the better the fix will be. Please feel free to go into extensive details and provide links, documentation, examples, etc. we can check to get a solid grasp of the issue we have to fix.

Sending feedback

We’re not saying you should implement a support of script yourself if we don’t support it at all or very well, but it is noteworthy that we can’t necessarily get all the details right, especially when we don’t know how to speak and write the language you wish were supported or improved.

If our font-stacks are not good enough, a solider one will help. If we don’t have any font-stack for a language, a basic one will do. Additionally, you can point us to libre/open-source fonts which you think should be recommended to implementers.

If we’ve got something wrong in terms of typography, an example – picture, codepen demo, etc. – will help us see how we got there. Please bear in mind we might be limited by what web browsers can do though, and some issues could be consequently deemed “out of scope.” We will at least do our best to report the issue to whom it may concern whenever possible.

Check our contribution guidelines for further details.

Overarching issues

Implementers should be aware there are overarching issues for which we haven’t reached consensus, or couldn’t discuss yet.

The most important issue, by very far, is that checking the writing-mode at runtime can blow performance in extreme ways. It can indeed take 15 seconds to render some complex XHTML files in vertical-*. Needless to say, this would obviously be worse in terms of UX. And this is the reason why we try to guess the writing-mode from the OPF file.

Longer terms issues include:

polyfilling -epub-properties for web apps;
mixed directions (LTR document in a RTL publication) and mixed writing modes (horizontal-tb document in a vertical-rl publication);
support for alternate stylesheets, which is critical if the implementer wants to offer a horizontal/vertical-writing user setting;
support for rendition: align-x-center;
support for ibooks:respect-image-size-class (gaiji) and ibooks:scroll-axis metadata items (see EPUB Compat doc);
rendition: flow of scrolled-doc.

Out of scope

There are some typography and layout issues which are not the responsibility of apps’ implementers but rendering engines’. Those issues include:

line-adjustment and justification (RTL and CJK);
run-in headings (display: run-in), which is popular in CJK;
ruby and its styling;
bidi;
Kashida Elongation (Arabic);
joining forms (Arabic);
single-letter styling (Arabic).

If those issues arise, please report them to whom it may concern (e.g. Chromium, Firefox, Microsoft, Webkit, etc.). The entire web platform will indeed benefit. You can additionally report the issue to us so that we can document it for other implementers.

Glossary

Check the i18n Glossary doc for a glossary of terms you may encounter during bug reports, issues, or feedbacks.

Internationalization – A Typography Primer

[Implementers’ doc]

The aim of this document is to provide implementers with a typography baseline for internationalization.

Abstract

Various scripts and/or languages can vary from the typography rules implementers may be accustomed to in Latin. There are important idiosyncrasies to take into account, as it will impact the text layout of documents, base and default styles, and user settings.

The best way to keep up with best practices and requirements is the International text layout and typography index. In case of doubt, do not hesitate to check this index.

Fonts

In some scripts, it is common to use different fonts for headings or emphasis, rather than bolding or italicisation. For instance, Chinese, Japanese and Korean fonts almost always lack italic or oblique faces, because those are not native typographic traditions.

Proper italic glyphs in Cyrillic text can look very different from normal variants, so synthesising italics can produce poor results. This is the reason why implementers should make sure they provide an italic style for the Cyrillic fonts they are offering to users.

Special OpenType features may need to be supported, especially for the Arabic script, which needs ligatures.

Complex scripts have rules about how characters combine in syllabic structures, and scripts like Arabic may need controls to indicate where ligatures are wanted or not wanted. Authors may consequently use the zero-width joiner and zero-width non-joiner characters to force or disable ligatures, which can impact some features like search.

In CJK, fonts must support both horizontal and vertical writing modes, and extra attention must be paid as some characters will change depending on the writing mode of the document. It is for instance important to be able to convert between half-width and full-width presentation forms, and make sure the correct quotation marks are used – they are not the same depending on the writing mode.

Text decoration

Underlines need to be broken in special ways for some scripts, and the height of underlines, strike-through and overlines may vary depending on the script.

For vertical text the placement needs to be to the right or left of the line of text, rather than under or over.

Emphasis

Bold and italic are not always appropriate for expressing emphasis, and some scripts have their own unique ways of doing it.

In Japanese, a sans-serif font, or emphasis dots (horizontal writing) and sesame (vertical writing) may be used to express emphasis.

In the Amharic Script (Ethiopic), underlines, larger text or a different color may be used to express emphasis.

In Tibetan, marks and colors may be used to express emphasis.

Line breaking

In some scripts like Chinese and Japanese, text is set solid, which means there is no space between words. These scripts tend to break a line in the middle of a word (with no hyphenation) – even in Korean, which has spaces between words.

It would be strange to offer a word-spacing setting to users in those languages, and letter-spacing may create extra justification issues you won’t be able to resolve, for lack of more precise controls.

It is common for certain characters to be forbidden at the start or end of a line, but which characters these are, and what rules are applied when depends on the script or language. In some cases, such as Japanese, there may be different rules according to the type of content or the user's preference.

Hyphenation

Although CJK doesn’t use hyphenation, documents may contain other scripts which use hyphenation e.g. Latin in Japanese.

Justification

Typographic conventions for full text justification depend on the writing system, the content language, and the calligraphic style of the text. Some scripts have complex methods the rendering engine doesn’t necessarily support.

Kashida elongation is not supported for the Arabic script for instance (text-justify), but authors may be using the tatweel joining character (see i18n glossary doc) to elongate some words.

Chinese and Japanese are using inter-character justification for instance, while Latin uses inter-word.

Indents

In some scripts like CJK, indents are really important. Implementers should not try to provide users with such a setting, or apply a default designed for Latin.

Vertical text

Implementers must not try to provide a setting allowing users to switch from the vertical to horizontal writing mode, and vice versa, unless they support alternate stylesheets and the publication provides one for each mode. Indeed, characters, punctuation, emphasis marks, quotes, and so on and so forth, depend on the writing mode used, and an automatic switch would provide users with a subpar experience.

It's common for content authors to want to mix short horizontal runs of text, such as the tate-chu-yoko i.e. 2-digit numbers (text-combine-upright) or acronyms (text-orientation), in a vertical text.

Hanging punctuation at the end of lines can help improve justification for CJK in the vertical writing mode, but may be considered strange in the horizontal writing mode in some languages.

In Mongolian, it would be unexpected to have text written horizontal-tb if it is not using the Cyrillic script. The Mongolian script is indeed written vertical-lr and, unlike Chinese, Japanese, and Korean, can’t be written horizontal-tb.

Readium CSS Further Details: Explaining the CSS Voodoo

[Implementers’ doc]

Some parts of Readium CSS might feel like CSS voodoo at first sight. The goal of this document is to clarify how those parts actually work.

The Internal Framework

Readium CSS ships with a minimum viable framework to typeset unstyled publications (ReadiumCSS-default.css). Layout is managed by the “base” styles, used for all publications.

This stylesheet is based on HTML Suggested Rendering. Consequently, it will work if the markup is semantic.

If you’re familiar with CSS preprocessors (LESS, SASS, Stylus, etc.), you already know how to use it. It indeed relies on variables and functions, which are available in vanilla CSS today.

What’s noteworthy is that you can customize the entire publication by setting CSS variables (a.k.a. custom properties) and either use AS-IS at runtime or compile as a static representation before runtime (PostCSS config coming soon).

The stylesheet will then use those variables defined at the :root level.

Finally, a simplified version of the font-size normalize is embedded in this stylesheet (see next section).

Variables you can set

Typefaces

--RS__compFontFamily

The typeface for headings. The value can be another variable e.g. var(-RS__humanistTf).

--RS__codeFontFamily

The typeface for code snippets. The value can be another variable e.g. var(-RS__monospaceTf).

Typography

--RS__typeScale

The scale to be used for computing all elements’ font-size. Since those font sizes are computed dynamically, you can set a smaller type scale when the user sets one of the largest font sizes.

Possible values: 1 | 1.067 | 1.125 (suggested default) | 1.2 | 1.25 | 1.333 | 1.414 | 1.5 | 1.618

The suggested default will accomodate most configurations, from small to large screens. Please note it is different from the --USER__typeScale suggested default, which was designed to accomodate the publisher’s styles.

--RS__baseFontSize

The default font-size for body copy. It will serve as a reference for all related computations.

--RS__baseLineHeight

The default line-height for all elements.

Vertical rhythm

--RS__flowSpacing

The default vertical margins for HTML5 flow content e.g. pre, figure, blockquote, etc.

--RS__paraSpacing

The default vertical margins for paragraphs.

--RS__paraIndent

The default text-indent for paragraphs.

Hyperlinks

--RS__linkColor

The default color for hyperlinks.

--RS__visitedColor

The default color for visited hyperlinks.

Accentuation colors

--RS__primaryColor

An optional primary accentuation color you could use for headings or any other element of your choice.

--RS__secondaryColor

An optional secondary accentuation color you could use for any element of your choice.

Font Size Normalize and the Type Scale

The assumption is that at least basic semantic elements’ font-size can be interpolated to a type scale, with minimal variation (±1–2 pixels difference for each element) in comparison to authors’ styles.

We’re using the calc() function to emulate the following:

h1 = base font-size × typeScale ^ 3 (power of 3) 
h2 = base font-size × typeScale ^ 2 (power of 2) 
h3 = base font-size × typeScale 
h4 = base font-size 
body = base font-size

In which typeScale can be customized to match the actual scale used in the publication. There lies the flexibility of this normalize.

Getting the type scale is a one-two punch:

parseInt of the computed font-size for a heading and the base (division = result)*
Math.pow(result, 1/n), in which n is 3 for h1 (cubic root) and 2 for h2 (square root).

* h3 stops here.

Then the font-size for each heading and body copy element will be recomputed based on this type scale.

Of course this approach is limited, there is little we can do to account for ids, classes, etc.

But it can at least be used for themes, or an opt-in user setting.

Dynamic leading

Readium CSS automagically finds the ideal line-height of the current font and font-size in use if the author hasn’t set an explicit value.

We’re using the current algorithm in the calc() function:

(1em + (2ex - 1ch) - ((1rem - 16px) * 0.1667)) * var(--RS__lineHeightCompensation))

Therefore, the line-height is:

1em = the size of the font-size;
2ex - 1ch = 2 x-height - 1 character width (0), in order to take the typeface’s proportions into account e.g. if the font has a small x-height, leading will be more solid, and vice versa;
1rem - 16px = the current user’s font-size minus the one at 100% (base font-size);
0.1667 = a scale which has been defined from an optimal range (it is a magic number which has been retro-engineered from a set containing hundreds of samples);
var(--RS__lineHeightCompensation) is a factor (integer) to compensate a less than ideal line-height, especially in non-Latin scripts, where fonts tend to be square-ish.

This isn’t a perfect solution though, and this algorithm may be revisited in the future. Indeed, caveats are:

leading also depends on line-length, which is not addressed in the algorithm itself, line-length must therefore be constrained by other means – we couldn’t rely on the viewport width anyway;
sometimes, the User Agent default font-size is not 16px (e.g. Kindle experimental browser, user setting a larger font-size, etc.);
0.1667 feels like a magic number, or at least a weird number as it was retrofitted after testing hundreds of typefaces;
it’s clearly a natural logarithmic function i.e. it increases rapidly and then slows towards a zero rate of change, which will give mediocre results for very large font sizes (e.g. 400%);
it doesn’t work ideally for slab serif fonts with a large x-height, thick stroke and medium character width i.e. square-ish metrics – we don’t have any in the default font-stacks so we had to introduce a compensation factor to address this particular issue.

Conditional Selectors for user settings

Use settings are appended on load and won’t have any effect until a user-setting variable is set.

In order to do that, we must use “conditional selectors.” Problem is there is no if/else statements in CSS so how do we achieve this?

:root[style*="--USER__variable"]

Attribute selectors with pseudo-regex.

As soon as you set a property and its required flag to the html (or root) element, the user setting applies.

Whenever needed, we’re leveraging explicit inheritance (inherit value) so that the :root value can be passed throughout the DOM.

We’re also relying on the :not() pseudo-class to exclude some elements. Think of it as the following command prompt: “make all elements in the DOM inherit the value, excepted this one and that one.”

Performance of those selectors should not necessarily be a major concern. Indeed, authors’ stylesheets (weight, complexity, etc.) and expensive properties will have a much larger impact on performance.

The biggest issue with this is that it requires some time to get accustomed to, as it objectively feels like some kind of CSS trick borderline to CSS voodoo. It has proved reliable during testing though, and already deals with user settings issues other Reading Systems might have had troubles addressing so far. In addition, it automagically forces the necessary recalc some user settings absolutely require.

Themes

In this design model, themes can be a simple set of user settings. They consequently can be treated as objects you can parse to add properties to the html (root) element, and stringify to save/cache if the user creates a custom theme. No extra stylesheet needed.

Readium CSS Variables API

[Implementers’ doc]

This document is meant to list all the customizable medias and flags (to be found in ReadiumCSS-config.css), as well as all the CSS variables for Reading System and User styles available in the dist stylesheets.

As a reminder, the priority is, in general:

USER > AUTHOR > RS

How to set and remove user preferences

Setting a user preference

var root = document.documentElement; root.style.setProperty("--USER__var", "value");

You don’t need to remove the variable before setting another value, the new value will simply override the existing one.

Removing a user preference

var root = document.documentElement; root.style.removeProperty("--USER__var");

Customizable medias

You will find those customizable medias in ReadiumCSS-config.css. The values defined are used in media queries to control use of the auto pagination model.

--responsive-columns

Default is 60em

The min-width at which the auto pagination model must be used – will switch from 1 to 2 columns and vice versa.

--min-device-columns

Default is 36em

The minimum device width of the mobile device for which the auto pagination model must be used.

--max-device-columns

Default is 47em

The maximum device width of the mobile device for which the auto pagination model must be used.

Warning: if you customize those medias, all ReadiumCSS dist stylesheets must be rebuilt.

Customizable flags

You will find those customizable flags in ReadiumCSS-config.css, and can think of the preset values as boolean inline styles: if they are set on the :root element (i.e. html) then the flag is enabled. If another value is, or they are removed, then the flag is disabled.

Those custom selectors can only be customized before runtime. You could for example use a class or a custom attribute instead of an inline style. Check the “User Settings” and “Quickstart” docs for further details.

Note: The preset is not a default implementers should use. Indeed, the initialization of those flags depends on your user settings’ management e.g. apply user settings to all EPUBs, only the ones that have already been customized, etc.

:--paged-view

Preset: --USER__view: readium-paged-on

Scope: html

Override class: Chrome (should be applied by any means necessary)

:--scroll-view

Preset: --USER__view: readium-scroll-on

Scope: html

Override class: Chrome (should be applied by any means necessary)

:--font-override

Preset: --USER__fontOverride: readium-font-on

Scope: html

Override class: None. This flag is required to change the font-family user setting.

:--advanced-settings

Preset: --USER__advancedSettings: readium-advanced-on

Scope: html

Override class: None. This flag is required to apply the font-family, the font-size and/or advanced user settings.

:--sepia-mode

Preset: --USER__appearance: readium-sepia-on

Scope: html

Override class: Chrome (should be applied by any means necessary)

This flag applies the sepia reading mode.

:--night-mode

Preset: --USER__appearance: readium-night-on

Scope: html

Override class: Chrome (should be applied by any means necessary)

This flag applies the night reading mode.

:--darken-filter

Preset: --USER__darkenImages: readium-darken-on

Scope: html

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

This will only apply in night mode to darken images and impact img.

:--invert-filter

Preset: --USER__invertImages: readium-invert-on

Scope: html

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

This will only apply in night mode to invert images and impact img.

:--a11y-normalize

Preset: --USER__a11yNormalize: readium-a11y-on

Scope: html

Required flag: :--fontOverride

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

It impacts font style, weight and variant, text decoration, super and subscripts.

Warning: if you customize those flags, all ReadiumCSS dist stylesheets must be rebuilt.

Reading System Styles

Custom properties for the Reading System are prefixed with --RS__.

Pagination

--RS__colWidth

The optimal column’s width. It serves as a floor in our design.

--RS__colCount

The optimal number of columns (depending on the columns’ width).

--RS__colGap

The gap between columns. It must be set in pixels so that it won’t resize with font size.

You must account for this gap when scrolling.

--RS__pageGutter

The horizontal page margins. It must be set in pixels so that it won’t resize with font size.

--RS__maxLineLength

The optimal line-length. It must be set in rem in order to take :root’s font-size as a reference, whichever the body’s font-size might be.

Safeguards

--RS__maxMediaWidth

The max-width for media elements i.e. img, svg, audio and video.

--RS__maxMediaHeight

The max-height for media elements i.e. img, svg, audio and video.

--RS__boxSizingMedia

The box model (box-sizing) you want to use for media elements.

--RS__boxSizingTable

The box model (box-sizing) you want to use for tables.

Default font-stacks

--RS__oldStyleTf

An old style serif font-stack relying on pre-installed fonts.

Default is "Iowan Old Style", "Sitka Text", Palatino, "Book Antiqua", serif.

--RS__modernTf

A modern serif font-stack relying on pre-installed fonts.

Default is Athelas, Constantia, Georgia, serif.

--RS__sansTf

A neutral sans-serif font-stack relying on pre-installed fonts.

Default is -apple-system, system-ui, BlinkMacSystemFont, "Segoe UI", Roboto, "Helvetica Neue", Arial, sans-serif.

--RS__humanistTf 

A humanist sans-serif font-stack relying on pre-installed fonts.

Default is Seravek, Calibri, Roboto, Arial, sans-serif.

--RS__monospaceTf 

A monospace font-stack relying on pre-installed fonts.

Default is "Andale Mono", Consolas, monospace.

Default font-stacks for Japanese publications

--RS__serif-ja

A Mincho font-stack whose fonts with proportional latin characters are prioritized for horizontal writing.

Default is "ＭＳ Ｐ明朝", "MS PMincho", "Hiragino Mincho Pro", "ヒラギノ明朝 Pro W3", "游明朝", "YuMincho", "ＭＳ 明朝", "MS Mincho", "Hiragino Mincho ProN", serif.

--RS__sans-serif-ja

A Gothic font-stack whose fonts with proportional latin characters are prioritized for horizontal writing.

Default is "ＭＳ Ｐゴシック", "MS PGothic", "Hiragino Kaku Gothic Pro W3", "ヒラギノ角ゴ Pro W3", "Hiragino Sans GB", "ヒラギノ角ゴシック W3", "游ゴシック", "YuGothic", "ＭＳ ゴシック", "MS Gothic", "Hiragino Sans", sans-serif.

--RS__serif-ja-v

A Mincho font-stack whose fonts with fixed-width latin characters are prioritized for vertical writing.

Default is "ＭＳ 明朝", "MS Mincho", "Hiragino Mincho Pro", "ヒラギノ明朝 Pro W3", "游明朝", "YuMincho", "ＭＳ Ｐ明朝", "MS PMincho", "Hiragino Mincho ProN", serif.

--RS__sans-serif-ja-v

A Gothic font-stack whose fonts with fixed-width latin characters are prioritized for vertical writing.

Default is "ＭＳ ゴシック", "MS Gothic", "Hiragino Kaku Gothic Pro W3", "ヒラギノ角ゴ Pro W3", "Hiragino Sans GB", "ヒラギノ角ゴシック W3", "游ゴシック", "YuGothic", "ＭＳ Ｐゴシック", "MS PGothic", "Hiragino Sans", sans-serif.

Base styles for all ebooks

--RS__baseFontFamily

The default typeface for body copy in case the ebook doesn’t have one declared.

Please note some languages have a specific font-stack (japanese, chinese, hindi, etc.)

--RS__baseLineHeight

The default line-height for body copy in case the ebook doesn’t have one declared.

Default colors for all ebooks

--RS__textColor

The default color for body copy’s text.

--RS__backgroundColor

The default background-color for pages.

--RS__selectionBackgroundColor

The background-color for selected text.

It is worth noting it can be customized for each reading mode.

--RS__selectionTextColor

The color for selected text.

It is worth noting it can be customized for each reading mode.

Default styles for unstyled publications

Typefaces

--RS__compFontFamily

The typeface for headings. The value can be another variable e.g. var(-RS__humanistTf).

--RS__codeFontFamily

The typeface for code snippets. The value can be another variable e.g. var(-RS__monospaceTf).

Typography

--RS__typeScale

The scale to be used for computing all elements’ font-size. Since those font sizes are computed dynamically, you can set a smaller type scale when the user sets one of the largest font sizes.

Possible values: 1 | 1.067 | 1.125 | 1.2 (suggested default) | 1.25 | 1.333 | 1.414 | 1.5 | 1.618

--RS__baseFontSize

The default font-size for body copy. It will serve as a reference font all related computations.

--RS__baseLineHeight

The default line-height for all elements.

Vertical rhythm

--RS__flowSpacing

The default vertical margins for HTML5 flow content e.g. pre, figure, blockquote, etc.

--RS__paraSpacing

The default vertical margins for paragraphs.

--RS__paraIndent

The default text-indent for paragraphs.

Hyperlinks

--RS__linkColor

The default color for hyperlinks.

--RS__visitedColor

The default color for visited hyperlinks.

Accentuation colors

--RS__primaryColor

An optional primary accentuation color you could use for headings or any other element of your choice.

--RS__secondaryColor

An optional secondary accentuation color you could use for any element of your choice.

Reading Modes

Custom properties for reading modes are prefixed with --RS__.

--RS__backgroundColor

The background-color which must be applied to the entire screen in the reading mode.

--RS__textColor

The color for text in the reading mode.

--RS__linkColor

The color for the links in the reading mode.

--RS__visitedColor

The color for visited links in the reading mode.

--RS__selectionBackgroundColor

The background-color for selected text in the reading mode.

--RS__selectionTextColor

The color for selected text in the reading mode.

User Settings

Custom properties for user settings are prefixed with --USER__.

--USER__colCount

The number of columns (column-count) the user wants displayed (one-page view or two-page spread).

Scope: html

Possible values: 1 | 2 | auto (default)

Required flag: none

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To reset, change the value to auto.

--USER__pageMargins

A factor applied to horizontal margins (padding-left and padding-right) the user wants to set.

Scope: html

It impacts body.

Recommended values: a range from 0.5 to 2. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: none

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To reset, change the value to 1.

--USER__backgroundColor

The background-color for the whole screen.

Scope: html

It impacts all elements in the DOM.

Possible values: Color HEX (e.g. #FFFFFF), rgb(a), hsl.

Required flag: none

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To reset, remove the CSS variable.

--USER__textColor

The color for textual contents.

Scope: html

It impacts all elements but headings and pre in the DOM.

Possible values: Color HEX (e.g. #FFFFFF), rgb(a), hsl.

Required flag: none

Override class: Chrome advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

To reset, remove the CSS variable.

--USER__textAlign

The alignment (text-align) the user prefers.

Scope: html

It impacts body, li, and p which are not children of blockquote and figcaption.

Possible values: left (LTR) or right (RTL) | justify

Required flag: :--advancedSettings

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Note: the value start can be used to let all rendering engines, excepted Trident (IE11) and EdgeHTML (Edge), automatically deal with left and right based on the direction (dir attribute) set for the document and its nested elements.

--USER__bodyHyphens

Enabling and disabling hyphenation.

Scope: html

It impacts body, p, li, div and dd.

Possible Values: auto | none

Required flag: :--advancedSettings

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Warning: for the time being, automatic hyphenation won’t work if you are using the Blink rendering engine (either via Chrome or a Webview) on ChromeOS, Linux and Windows. It indeed is not implemented yet and we recommend not trying to polyfill it using JavaScript as it will create a11y issues, especially with screen readers.

--USER__fontFamily

The typeface (font-family) the user wants to read with.

Scope: html

It impacts body, p, li, div, dt, dd and phrasing elements which don’t have a lang or xml:lang attribute.

Required flag: :--fontOverride

Override class: User settings (should be applied by any means necessary)

To reset, remove the required flag.

--USER__fontSize

Increasing and decreasing the root font-size. It will serve as a reference for the cascade.

Scope: html

Possible values: var(--RS__oldStyleTf) | var(--RS__modernTf) | var(--RS__sansTf) | var(--RS__humanistTf) | <string>

For Japanese, possible values become: var(--RS__serif-ja) (horizontal writing) | var(--RS__sans-serif-ja) (horizontal writing) | var(--RS__serif-ja-v) (vertical writing) | var(--RS__sans-serif-ja-v) (vertical writing) | <string>

Required flag: :--fontOverride

Override class: User settings (should be applied by any means necessary)

To reset, remove the required flag.

--USER__typeScale

The type scale the user wants to use for the publication.

Scope: html

It requires the ReadiumCSS-fs_normalize.css stylesheet.

It impacts headings, p, li, div, pre, dd, small, sub, and sup.

Recommended values: a range from 75% to 250%. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: :--advancedSettings

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

--USER__lineHeight

Increasing and decreasing leading (line-height).

Scope: html

It impacts body, p, li and div

Recommended values: a range from 1 to 2. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: :--advancedSettings

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

--USER__paraSpacing

The vertical margins (margin-top and margin-bottom) for paragraphs.

Scope: p

Recommended values: a range from 0 to 2rem. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: :--advancedSettings

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

--USER__paraIndent

The text-indent for paragraphs.

Scope: p

Recommended values: a range from 0 to 3rem. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: :--advancedSettings

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

--USER__wordSpacing

Increasing space between words (word-spacing, related to a11y).

Scope: h1, h2, h3, h4, h5, h6, p, li, div

Recommended values: a range from 0 to 1rem. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: :--advancedSettings

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

--USER__letterSpacing

Increasing space between letters (letter-spacing, related to a11y).

Scope: h1, h2, h3, h4, h5, h6, p, li, div

Recommended values: a range from 0 to 0.5rem. Increments are left to implementers’ judgment.

Required flag: :--advancedSettings

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

--USER__ligatures

Enabling and disabling ligatures in Arabic (related to a11y).

Scope: html

It impacts all text.

Possible values: none | common-ligatures

Required flag: :--advancedSettings

Override class: User settings advanced (optional but should be applied by any means necessary if provided to users)

Install, test and build Readium CSS

[Implementers’ doc]

Install and init references for regression tests

First, navigatate to the project’s folder in your terminal,

cd path/to/readium-css

then type:

npm install

This will install all dev dependencies needed and make npm scripts available to ease all processes you’ll need to run later.

Then, once the install is finished, type:

npm run test:ref

This will create reference screenshots for the CSS regression tests.

Build

We are using PostCSS, a tool for transforming CSS with JavaScript. It comes with a vast amount of task-oriented plugins and allows authors to use modern specs which are not implemented yet.

PostCSS official website
PostCSS tutorial
PostCSS plugins list

PostCSS Dependencies

ReadiumCSS is relying on a PostCSS config to build dist stylesheets. If you npm install the repository, all those dependencies will be installed as well.

Here is the current list of dependencies:

stylelint (link);
postcss-cli (link);
postcss-import (link);
postcss-sorting (link);
postcss-custom-media (link);
postcss-custom-selectors (link);
postcss-discard-comments (link);
postcss-css-variables (link) [disabled];
postcss-alter-property-value (link) [disabled].

Build dist stylesheets

If you customize ReadiumCSS-config.css, you will have to rebuild stylesheets.

Note: the current build process is subpar – to say the least. Please feel free to improve it (gulp, grunt, etc.).

Available scripts

By default, the following scripts are available:

build, will build all stylesheets;
build:ltr, will build default stylesheets (Left to Right scripts);
build:rtl, will build stylesheets for Right to Left scripts;
build:cjk, will build stylesheets for Chinese, Japanese, and Korean in horizontal writing mode;
build:vertical, will build stylesheets for Chinese, Japanese, Korean, and Mongolian in vertical writing mode.

Those scripts will overwrite the files in the css/dist folder, the stylesheets you’ll use in your app.

Usage

First navigate to the readium-css folder if you didn’t already, then…

npm run build

Building dist stylesheets for browsers which don’t support CSS variables

If you need to build stylesheets for IE11 or an early version of Edge (e.g. 14), then you can use most of ReadiumCSS, excepted user settings. You’ll consequently have to customize the src’s ReadiumCSS-before.css, ReadiumCSS-default.css and ReadiumCSS-after.css and remove the user settings submodules.

Then you must customize the selectors in ReadiumCSS-config.js and replace them with either CSS classes or custom attributes so that reading modes and flags can work as expected.

Finally you will have to enable the postcss-css-variables and postcss-alter-property-value in the postcss.config.js file to be found at the src folder’s root.

The following must be added to plugins:

require("postcss-css-variables")({ 
  "preserve": true 
}), 
require("postcss-alter-property-value")({ 
  declarations: { 
    "*": { 
      task: "remove" 
    , whenValueEquals: "undefined" 
    } 
  } 
})

This will:

interpolate CSS variables into a static representation, while preserving variables for other browsers ("preserve": true);
remove static representations which can’t be interpolated and are undefined (remove task).

We recommend managing user settings via JavaScript in this case, especially as you can test support for CSS variables, as described in the CSS Variables primer.

Useful PostCSS plugins

Here is a list of additionnal PostCSS plugins which might prove useful to implementers.

Unprefix EPUB properties: EPUB interceptor
Adding vendor prefixes: Autoprefixer

Test

Once you have build dist stylesheets, you can run regression tests using Backstop.js.

It helps you check if you didn’t accidentally create a breaking change when customizing stylesheets, and make sure pagination, reading modes, and user settings work as expected.

Config

You will find the configuration file, backstop.json at the root of the project. By default, it runs those tests for a smartphone (portrait) and a tablet (landscape) viewports using Chrome, but you can customize it to fit your needs.

For instance, if you don’t need to support mobile, you could modify viewports:

"viewports": [ 
  { 
    "label": "desktop small", 
    "width": 800, 
    "height": 600 
  }, 
  { 
    "label": "desktop large", 
    "width": 1600, 
    "height": 900 
  } 
]

And if you want to run tests using Webkit instead of Blink because you’re developing iOS apps:

"engine": "phantomjs"

Test files

If you customize flags in ReadiumCSS-config.css, you must modify HTML files in the tests folder; user settings are indeed set as inline styles on the html element and are using the default flags.

Available scripts

By default, the following scripts are available:

test, will run tests;
test:ref, will create reference screenshots;
test:approve, will update reference screenshots from the current test.

Usage

First navigate to the readium-css folder if you didn’t already, then…

npm run test

The regression tests will run against the newly-created dist stylesheets, which is why you must build them beforehand.

Once all scenarios are tested for the viewports you created, which can take up to a minute, a report will automatically open in your browser.

If a unit test is marked as “failed”, it doesn’t necessarily mean the user setting failed, it just means you made a significant change which impacts rendering. Take a closer look at the diff, and if you’re happy with the result, head to the terminal and type:

npm run test:approve

This will make the current test screenshots the new reference for the next test.

Note: on some occasions, an error might happen during tests and the process won’t stop. Try ctrl + c to stop the current process and run the test again.

Fixed-layouts’ Reading Systems Requirements

[Implementers’ doc] [Authors’ doc]

Source: EPUB Content Documents 3.2

There’s a few criteria Reading Systems must meet in order to be conformant:

it should allocate the full content display area (i.e. as much of the available Viewport area as possible) for the document;
it must use the dimensions expressed in the viewport meta tag to render XHTML Content Documents;
it must use the dimensions expressed in the viewbox, and/or x, y, width and height attributes in SVG to render SVG Content Documents.

Styling

You should not inject additional content such as borders, margins, headers or footers into the viewport or the appplication area surrounding the viewport.

Scaling

XHTML (viewport meta)

When the aspect ratio does not match the aspect ratio of the Reading System, you may position the containing block inside the area to accommodate the user interface (letter-boxing).

Content positioned outside the containing block will not be visible.

SVG

SVG is a little bit more complex as there are different options to take into account.

Viewbox attribute

If the SVG only has a viewbox attribute, the coordinate system it defines is mapped to the viewport, keeping the aspect ratio.

Sizing and positioning attributes

If the pixel values defined by x, y, height and width exceed the viewport’s pixel values, the graphic must not be rescaled (it must be clipped on the viewport boundaries).

Both

The coordinate system defined by the viewbox is mapped to the viewport, keeping the aspect ratio.

Notes

The rendition:spread portrait and rendition:viewport are deprecated in EPUB 3.2.

Consequently, the rendition:spread-portrait spine override is deprecated as well.

E-production feedback and requests

[Implementers’ info]

One important part of the Readium CSS project is collecting feedback and queries from the e-production community (CSS authors). This is a summary.

CSS Authors’ typical profile

The typical CSS author has been doing e-production for 3 years or more (76%), is primarily concerned about interoperability (80%) and feels like he/she gets at least CSS fundamentals (88%). Most of his/her queries are related to layouts you can do in print but you can’t in ebooks yet.

A few notes:

interoperability implies Kindle, back to Mobi7 on the north-american market (Mobi7 is ± HTML 3.2);
specific versions of EPUB files for more advanced RS like iBooks or Readium exist, and this issue is partly related to distribution: authors don’t know the app the reader will use and don’t want risking rendering issues;
sometimes, specific versions mean authors (and/or software) will fall back to EPUB 2 files, in order to get around support uncertainty;
one key is probably progressive enhancement techniques, but that’s more of an education/evangelization issue and not in implementations’ scope per se.

Workflow and authoring

Workflow is still print-centric

From the feedback we could get, DTP software is still prevalent (more than 2/3 of answers), but automation is a thing (XML and even Node.js).

This means that should we provide new design options, change won’t happen overnight. Authors would have to add them to their workflow first (manual editing or automation upgrade), then authoring software would have to support them.

What’s interesting is that most authors would appreciate having such design options (more than 75%, on two polls), but if there isn’t any side-effects in other apps (cf. interoperability). Of course that would require production moving to EPUB 3 (EPUB 2 still makes up roughly 70% of all incoming content @ Kobo for instance).

So once again, we have an education/evangelization issue to deal with there.

Authoring practices

CSS authoring varies greatly.

Almost 2/3 of authors use a custom stylesheet that they adjust for every book, very few actually rely on the styles output by their DTP tools. As a consequence, there’s no consensus when it comes to the CSS selectors authors use. It can be:

p
.class
p.class
div.class p.class
[epub|type="semantic-inflection"] p
greatly-specified selectors with or without combinators (from actual samples).

Reasons include:

ease of use;
complexity and variety of the publication’s contents;
semantics (especially with epub:type);
production being outsourced with no specification – i.e. this is how the contractor do things.

If we want to solve the user settings issue well, we’ll probably have to find clever and inventive ways, selectors specificity being a dead-end in practice.

There’s a proposal for user agent properties and a draft for customization, they have some potential for upcoming files if EPUB gets a “do not touch my CSS” flag at some point – what’s already distributed is probably lost. With user agent properties, authors could design user-centric stylesheets so, in theory, RS could not override styles at all and just set values for those properties.

In the meantime, we have to “emulate” the cascade and resolve to !important. So that’s trying to make an unperfect mechanism into something more elegant, which requires a lot of fine-tuning.

Worries and issues

Worries

What bothers authors the most:

the app overriding styles without an explicit demand from the user (a.k.a. changing a setting);
the complete lack of control over page layout (margins, background, etc.);
user overrides which are all or nothing.

Interestingly, reading modes’ adjustments and user settings exposure are not priorities – which doesn’t mean they aren’t concerns. There are two assumptions we could make:

providing readers with images filters in night mode is probably the best first step we can make since a significant part of authors might not use extra markup to deal with it on an image-per-image basis (especially if no other RS supports it);
user settings exposure is probably one of the best practical ways to deal with non-binary user settings and overrides (cf. user agent properties proposal) so, once again, education/evangelization kicks in.

Issues

Top issues are, in order of priority:

images’ sizing e.g. author’s sizing is not respected, image is cut-off;
broken media queries (which makes responsive design impossible);
lack of support for modern CSS;
Math.

This shouldn’t come as a surprise; those are long-standing issues in need of practical solutions (media queries don’t work in columned-content) and fixes (flexbox, grid, and modern layout specs have a lot of bugs in columns’ implementations). Our best bet there is collaborating with the CSS-multicol spec editors since we’re probably one of the major use cases for this spec.

Popular requests

Unsurprisingly, a lot of requests are about layouts possible in print but not (yet) in e-books:

full bleed (container, image, background-color);
support for paged-media (running header/footer, float figures top/bottom, etc.);
vertical centering and alignment;
floated shapes (wrapping the image and not its bounding box);
option to put contents like page numbers, icons, etc. in the margins;
using a baseline grid;
forcing the chapter title as the running header;
proper support of page-breaks;
media queries for reading modes (sepia, night, etc.);
stylable popup footnotes.

A few notes:

in theory, putting contents in the margins and full-bleed are (almost) possible in Readium CSS: it depends on its implementation. Consequently, don’t be surprised if some authors make some experiments and raise issues;
some requests are already possible in some rendering engines: vertical-centering and alignment, floated shapes, and using a baseline grid is already possible on some platforms (depends on the web view/browser used) so it is more of an authors’ issue;
anything related to paged-media has had low traction at the browser vendors level so far, you’ll probably have to polyfill those features if you want to meet those expectations.

Interoperability issues reported

We care deeply about interoperability. Although Readium CSS has been designed from scratch, a lot of research has been put into other Reading Systems in order to improve interop (and not introduce breaking changes/side-effects). To our knowledge, we’re even the first project openly tackling EPUB implementations’ interoperability. Indeed, one of our main goals is to provide authors with a solid bedrock so Readium CSS should not become an issue for them.

A few interop issues have been reported:

page margins: some apps/devices have huge page margins, others don’t have any, it’s really hard for authors to know what they should be doing here (margin: 0 or margin: value);
support of existing specifications is lacking (the issue being that some existing specs are really hard to implement well in practice);
images optimization (this could be related to picture and srcset);
font obfuscation isn’t implemented everywhere, which is a huge issue for fixed-layout.

CSS Performance Hacks

[Implementers’ doc]

This document discusses the CSS specs implementers can use in case they have performance issues:

will-change;
CSS containment.

At first sight, using those 2 specs can give tremendous results but you sometimes have to use them in clever ways: it’s not just about adding a line of CSS in your stylesheet.

Will-change

The fundamental rule of will-change

Set will-change to the properties you’ll actually change, on the elements that are actually changing. And remove it when they stop.

Abstract

The will-change property allows an author to inform the UA ahead of time of what kinds of changes they are likely to make to an element. The UA can then try to optimize how they handle the element ahead of time, performing potentially-expensive work preparing for an animation before the animation actually begins.

In other words, will-change is a UA hint, it doesn’t have any styling effect on the elements for which you’re using it. It’s worth noting it can have appearance effects though, if a new stacking context is created.

It is, in many ways, an official property for the infamous “translate-z hack.” Although it was meant for animation, it can also deal with more simple changes.

Usage

will-change: <animateable-feature> = scroll-position || contents || <custom-ident>

Scroll-position

Indicates that the author expects to animate or change the scroll position of the element in the near future.

A browser might take this value as a signal to expand the range of content around the scroll window that is rendered, so that longer/faster scrolls can be done smoothly.

Contents

Indicates that the author expects to animate or change something about the element’s contents in the near future.

A browser might take this value as a signal to cache less aggressively on the element, or avoid caching at all and just continually re-render the element from scratch.

custom-ident

Indicates that the author expects to animate or change the property with the given name on the element in the near future.

A browser might take a value of transform as a signal that it should go ahead and promote the element to its own layer immediately, before the element starts to be transformed, to avoid any delay involved in rerendering the old and new layers.

Drawbacks

By using will-change, you’re basically telling the browser the element is a few moments away from changing, the browser consequently dedicates memory and resources to this element. If you use it for too many elements, it will thus degrade performance.

This property should be considered a last resort, it was not meant for premature optimization. You should use it only if you have to deal with performance issues.

Do’s and Dont’s

Do’s

Use will-change sparingly in stylesheets
Give will-change sufficient time to work
Use <custom-ident> to target super specific changes (left, opacity, etc.)
Use it in JavaScript if needed (add and remove hint)
Remove will-change after the changes are done

Dont’s

Don’t declare changes to too many properties
Don’t apply it to too many elements
Don’t waste resources on elements that have stopped changing

Examples

UI elements

Specifying will-change for a small number of persistent UI elements in a page which should react snappily to the user is appropriate:

body > .sidebar { 
	will-change: transform; 
	/* Will use 'transform' to slide it out when the user requests. */ 
}

Because this is limited to a small number of elements, the fact that the optimization is rarely actually used doesn’t hurt very much.

User click

If an element is going to change when a user clicks on it, setting will-change on hover will usually give at least 200 milliseconds for the optimizations to be set up, as human reaction time is relatively slow.

.element { 
	transition: opacity 0.2s; 
	opacity: 1; 
} 

.element:hover { 
	will-change: opacity; 
} 

.element:active { 
	opacity: 0.3; 
}

Adding and removing the hint with JavaScript

This is probably the way to go, should you try using will-change to optimize performance.

Here we have the hint added on :hover, then removed when the animation has ended.

var el = document.getElementById('element'); 

// Set will-change when the element is hovered 
el.addEventListener('mouseenter', hintBrowser); 
el.addEventListener('animationEnd', removeHint); 

function hintBrowser() { 
	// The optimizable properties that are going to change 
	// in the animation's keyframes block 
	this.style.willChange = 'transform, opacity'; 
} 

function removeHint() { 
	this.style.willChange = 'auto'; 
}

References

CSS Will Change Module Level 1
Can I Use
Mozilla Dev Network
Everything you need to know about the CSS will-change property
CSS ‘will-change’ Property: A Performance Case Study

CSS Containment

Note: This is only implemented in Blink (Chrome + Opera). It is under consideration for Microsoft Edge.

Abstract

The contain property indicates that the element and its contents are, as much as possible, independent of the rest of the page.

This allows the browser to recalculate layout, style, paint, size, or any combination of them for a limited area of the DOM and not the entire page. To put it simply, it lets developers limit the scope of the browser's styles, layout and paint work.

It was primarily meant for webpages which contain a lot of widgets that are all independent as it can be used to prevent one widget's CSS rules from changing other things on the page.

Usage

contain: strict || content || size || layout || style || paint

Strict

This is a shorthand for all values, it is equivalent to contain: size layout style paint.

Content

This is a shorthand for all values but size, it is equivalent to contain: layout style paint.

Size

It indicates that the element can be laid out without the need to examine its descendants.

Layout

It indicates that nothing outside can affect the element’s internal layout, and vice versa.

Style

It indicates that, for properties which can have effects on more than just an element and its descendants, those effects don’t escape the containing element.

Paint

It indicates that the descendants of the element don’t display outside its bounds, so if an element is off-screen or otherwise not visible, its descendants are also guaranteed to be not visible.

Possible optimizations

In theory, huge performance gains are possible, but it requires a solid knowledge of how browsers work and what causes reflow, relayout, repaint, etc. Judging by examples, I can see how it could be useful but we’ll probably have to find inventive and clever ways to leverage it since our scope is very often the root document.

If you need a refresher:

How browsers work
What force layout/reflow

Layout

When laying out the page, the contents of separate containing elements can be laid out in parallel, as they’re guaranteed not to affect each other.
When laying out the page, if the containing element is off-screen or obscured and the layout of the visible parts of the screen do not depend on the size of the containing element (for example, if the containing element is near the end of a block container, and you’re viewing the beginning of the block container), the layout of the containing elements' contents can be delayed or done at a lower priority.
Layout is normally document-scoped so if you change an element's left property, every single element in the DOM might need to be checked. Enabling containment here can potentially reduce the number of elements to just a handful, rather than the whole document, saving the browser a ton of unnecessary work and significantly improving performance.

Style

Whenever a property is changed on a descendant of the containing element, calculating what part of the DOM tree is “dirtied” and might need to have its style recalculated can stop at the containing element.
Containment here is purely about limiting the parts of the tree that are under consideration when styles are mutated, not when they are declared.

Paint

If the containing element is off-screen or obscured, the UA can directly skip trying to paint its contents, as they’re guaranteed to be off-screen/obscured as well.
Unless the clipped content is made accessible via a separate mechanism such as the overflow, resize, or text-overflow properties, the UA can reserve “canvas” space for the element exactly the element’s size.
Because they are guaranteed to be stacking contexts, scrolling elements can be painted into a single GPU layer.
It acts as a containing block for absolutely positioned and fixed position elements: any children are positioned based on the element, not the document.
It becomes a stacking context: things like z-index will have an effect on the element, and children will be stacked according to the new context.
It becomes a new formatting context: a block level element will be treated as a new, independent layout environment. Layout outside of the element won’t typically affect the containing element's children.

Size

It ensures you don’t rely on child elements for sizing, but by itself it doesn’t offer much performance benefit.

References

CSS Containment Module Level 1
Can I Use
Mozilla Dev Network
CSS Containment in Chrome 52